alright here we go ready let's turn it on wow wow look that's crazy what are they
those revealed from the depths of the jungle looking for evidence of the Mayan War
I am Albert the engineer, there is a forgotten world there, lost cities hidden in the jungle and
National Geographic Explorer the border of the Mayan World is right under our feet I'm in
a mission to uncover the secrets of one of the most mysterious ancient civilizations in the
the Mayans and now technology shows us a completely new story reveals
An ancient civilization in Central America has been much more complex than archaeologists believed.
In 201 National Geographic broke the news of an incredible discovery: an ancient city from 600
constructions
Esteli is the most important site in Mayan archaeology in 100 years, and from the ground up it gives you chills.
on the back using the technology that can see through the dense jungle like
an x-ray ready to see it without trees discovered more than 60,000 structures made
by man on an incredible new treasure map wow look that we did it is very distressing
Now with the new map further back, some of the archaeologists can take it further apart.
The most intrepid people in the world will be dangerous, of course they are taking over the jungle. B, there is a painted container.
has something written in search of its secrets we have a skeleton all in one search
to rewrite the amazing history of the
Mayan secrets of the
Mayans the Mayan snake very well for me the Mayans
They have always been one of the most ancient civilizations
Fascinating but much of what we thought we knew is wrong down there right now.
is being completely rewritten armed with this new treasure map archaeologists are
On a voyage of discovery but on a large scale this time I investigate the Mayans in
war unearthing a rare ritual altar This is the moment we've been waiting for a year
Ephraim Ephraim Ephraim with ties to one of the most ruthless of all the Mayan dynasties explore
an ancient site that saw massive conflict something happened right here here people died
and I'm going to follow one of the most surprising of all the new discoveries, go this is it
It is surprising that there is a complete reversal of everything that experts thought they knew about the war.
I feel my heart racing now as the old ones
Mayas deep in the jungles of Central America the archaeologist
Guatemalan Edwin Romá Ramírez is on a [Music] mission heading
to a remote mountain range in search of the Mayans ready for action
The Mayans emerged 3000 years ago in Central America in the region that
Today is Guatemala, southern Mexico and the countries
adjacent Mayans tamed the jungle creating cities of scale and
dazzling complexity forging a civilization that lasted more than 2000 years
But besides all its glory there was a brutal side of blood and
human sacrifices But apart from the inscriptions and carvings little
It is known about how Edwin fought his wars that the house of new
evidence exploring in the depths of the jungle outside
from an ancient city called the soots in the far north of
Guatemala is working with fellow archaeologist and National Geographic explorer
Tom Gison These data from the laar are incredible in the new high-tech map can
Seeing evidence of huge man-made structures seems like we have a Causeway
important running along the side of this cliff face before these buildings were
completely hidden under the jungle are now totally exposed I think maybe
If you start here and go up take a look at what looks like something very big maybe a
land formation looks like a very large Tom and Edwin think that the newly built buildings
identified could reveal some unique clues to the Mayan war, I'm just saying, look at these
features here this one has almost 8 Met height 8 Met Tom although we are not going to
know until you go and check it out This will be exciting good That's perfect Thank you
Tom we see the new map reveals a mysterious series of buildings along 4 km
across a steep summit all apparently connected to a set of structures at the base
The oppressive heat, dense vegetation and deadly wildlife make
from this one of the most extreme borders of the
archaeology I love being here I like the sounds of the
Jungle Edwin has 15 seasons working under these harsh conditions
conditions to be with people who love and have the same passion
that one has for this is really incredible but it is the first time with the new map of the
Treasure, we are walking along an old road you can see
that lidar shows us that we are walking there but it is difficult
See him then suddenly in the dense jungle, wow, look, we did it, it's huge, Edwin.
notice something on the top of the mountain, an ancient pyramid hidden for centuries
and it appears that the pyramid is just one of a group of structures all revealed by the new
technology let's go
Yes, the new treasure map is the result of a massive study that covers more than 2,000 km.
Jungle Square University of Houston National Center for Laser Mapping
The initiative, called Pacun Laider, brings together an international consortium.
One of the engineers behind the study is Juan Carlos Fernández Díaz.
his team flies a plane over the dense foliage of the
jungle using high-tech scanning equipment billions
Laser pulses are fired downwards and bounce back. The technique is called
We measure the time it takes for the pulse to leave the plane and the return of these reflexes. Knowing
the speed of light time it takes we can find out the distance between the plane and each one
Of these reflections, whether the tree tops or the ground, only a small fraction
of the pulses reach the ground for archaeological studies in the jungle we want to get rid of
all the points that come from the vegetation and stay only with the ground and the buildings
ancient Once all the unwanted pulses coming from the trees are filtered out
The data left behind allows engineers to build a 3D map of the
hidden ground in the [Music] jungle University of California San Diego San Diego California
This is where I research using digital technologies to explore
the ancient world and have been given very special access to explore the new ones.
large scale data This is what the jungle looks like from above but when you roll clear the
trees appear countless structures made by the
man in total about 60,000 structures have been revealed
hidden two of the project leaders the explorers of
hanida Look at that magic Look at that Look wow It's almost as if we were flying over the Mayan World in
a helicopter That's the most exciting thing about laar teaches us humility there are things
What the data teaches us all is that we are not just talking about one city.
New are dozens is a scale discovery all when I saw the first bundle come out I said that
It's the future, that's what we have to do. We're back to the old way.
Mayan city of El The new map led Edwin Román Ramírez to a discovery
Spectacular At the top of this mountain is hidden a pyramid
ancient observe this structure here you see it that is exactly what it showed us
liar It's really amazing Wow this building was maybe completed between 350 and 600
After Christ, what is incredible is that around here you can still see some of the walls of
Beyond the pyramids Edwin finds more ruins looks like a small plaza right here
and surrounding everyone with giant walls I don't really know how to describe it
It's just a huge wall, all predictions delar but this new
site with benches and walls does not look like a typical Mayan city [Music] and its
discovery could solve a mystery about the Mayan wars, well this is it
Incredible Edwin Rom Ramirez follows the new Laar treasure map to a discovery
surprising the ruins of what Edwin believes was once a vast citadel
fortified protected by la cresta de la montaña y cercado huge walls
This is an innovative discovery because throughout the Mayan World
Permanent defenses on such a scale have almost never been
found before the liar map experts believed that the Mayans resolved their conflicts in
a very unusual way they thought that everything was ritualized involving only the
capture and sacrifice of Kings but new evidence suggests something very
different on the giant screen the mountain fortress of
Edwin is evidence of a war on a scale
colossal look at that peak if this is amazing it cannot be denied
that this is a Mayan fortress you can see large systems of trenches and sand walls
it is a height
considerable This is a very protected area now We are seeing
towards the west And as we move towards the next pair of peaks we begin
to see solitary stone structures and this could be a tower system
Lookout or surveillance towers, lookout towers, you see that one over there, yes, of course, they are monitoring this
Verac landscape like this we know that there was an environment of
conflict This is a fortress it is a military installation these people were in
[Music] War Edwin returns from the fortified summit because
On the floor of the Valley there are remains of others
buildings here have already begun excavations and in one of the first test pits I don't think so
Look at this incredible beautiful there is a shocking discovery it is a great find a tip of
incredibly rare and perfectly preserved flint spear with over
1 years old wow it's amazing maybe we'll find more things history of this
strength this is really amazing because it is complete It is really amazing to me
finding something like this is very impressive a spearhead fortified walls and a
Line of watchtowers leave archaeologists in no doubt This is an environment
of war this is compelling evidence of war right in the heart of the world
Maya it is incredible to think that in all this deserted jungle There was once a landscape of fear and
conflict on a scale that experts had never imagined until studies with liar
But I want to explore the evidence of war for myself.
The site I'm going to is so remote that it can only be reached by helicopter and then by the
River is the age of discovery this is what it's all about
Yes, I'm going to join Puerto Rican archaeologist Alcover far beyond the test area.
From Pacun he is part of a team that is taking archaeology to a whole new level
Again, this is no man's land. Where we are, we are basically in international waters.
The river is shared by Mexico and Guatemala and is one of the natural borders between the two
countries 2000 years ago these banks were home to two rival Mayan prisoners.
ancient Mayan city called Piedras Negras and a macabil nearby group of ruins barely
explored in both places cutting-edge technology is revealing evidence
increasingly surprising about the Mayans at war [Music]
The sun is now beginning to rise and the temperature is
elevate This is going to be a great challenge I'm going to climb a little more bionic than most but
It's worth it, this jungle has secrets to reveal and we're going to find them right now.
I'm climbing through the isolated mountain jungle with archaeologist Omar
for the Mayans this would have been the same
This is one of the densest jungles I have ever traveled through, it is old and overgrown and cannot be crossed.
see beyond 15 or 30 met enier direc everything is completely green the challenge is trying to find
Something in all this fortunately for us we have technology is well ready we are going to
turn it on great s Look that's crazy What are they are just
stones build this when data collected on an augmented reality platform suddenly Al
clearing the trees I can see a wall that stretches about 100 meters across
The hillside is like an x-ray through the trees, it's very curious, let's see it. Yes
come on it's amazing to think that each of these blocks was cut and
carried by hand but until Omar combined thousands of close-up photographs
plane in a single model it was impossible to see the entire line of the wall from
far away and what it reveals is the incredible effort made by the Mayans to defend themselves from the
attacks the fact that they built more than seven of these on top of a mountain
It means that the threat of a violent encounter was very real, something happened right here, here they died
people Yes it is very likely you come running you try to attack you are running you hit these
rocks and then suddenly they attack you with wave stones or just loose rocks that they throw
This is another fortress built by a threatened community more than 2000 years ago.
years right at the ends of the Mayan World along with the citadel of Edwin near the
These discoveries are changing our whole idea of wars. [Music]
[Music] Mayans it's been a very very hard day
But there is much more to see throughout the jungle and we will have to wait until
morning and it's raining again
[Music]
100 km east of Omar's fortress and back within the
Laar study area is already daylight and they have better
Climate is good news for archaeologist Marchelo [Music] Canuto has the mission
to explore another totally new discovery revealed by
It is relatively large here we can see several buildings 1 2 3 4 5 and there are
a kind of Maybe three buildings here or maybe it's a small platform marchelo ha
spent more than a decade investigating an ancient Mayan site called the
Crown is his first field season since the study of
bacun and on this giant screen marchelo will see the crown as he has never seen it before
So hidden behind those trees find the crown yes hidden between
those swamps and hidden under those trees is the main part of the crown right
Okay, go look, that's great, look at that, observe. Wow, that's the place. That's it. That's it.
great to see it like that it's coming out of the trees yes Exactly How long
You've been doing this, we've been working since 2005, 2005, 2005, just this year you're able to see the
data of the leader yes exact and it is the first time that we are seeing the whole site in one
single image Nobody knows the crown better than Marcelo but the liar map too
surprised Look, there is a large causeway that I hadn't seen before right there
after that core group right there
Look, look at those two small parallel lines. That's right, that's right, and what's in
reality they do It's that this is amazing this Calzada connects with another group that never
We had previously investigated, you didn't know about that part, no, no, I didn't know anything about this really.
I didn't know anything about this until I saw this data. I had never seen this road before.
and it is not the only discovery revealed by
Furthermore, beyond the new Calzada there is another previously unknown site
heading to the field outside the Marchelo crown Investigate It's time
[Music] Well before the studies Deidar Marchelo would never have found
Nothing hidden in this [Music] jungle Oh yeah that's right on target There
It's there, it's the main structure, it's not great, it's
The Great This is the main structure the map
has brought to Marchelo some ancient remains completely new to archaeology and there it is
the other There it is These are the two main structures on the site we were looking for
It is a huge find, an entire settlement less than a day's walk north of the
crown future excavations will try to reveal more about this site and also about
the [Music] crown in the simplest way possible today we find a new site is
A good day is a very good day [Music] back at the main site in the crown
Excavations have been underway for over a decade and are still being extracted.
Treasures [Music] Working in a place like the Crown is almost a full-time job
After 12 years it becomes part of your life so of course it's the
special place for all of us because we have dedicated our professional lives to this
One of the biggest finds of all is being made this season in this field
a monument carved in
Marchelo stone made the discovery under a collapsed temple in one of
the great squares of the crown right in the heart of the old
city the carved monuments contain clues to one of the
The most powerful royal dynasties that the Mayans knew The Kings
For more than a century, experts have worked to decipher Mayan writing.
and much of it remains a mystery but they have been able to decipher the story
of the serpent kings who rose in the north and conquered city after city including the crown
It is the beginning of a crucial day in the
Corona Marchelo and his team are preparing to raise the beautiful monument and
transport it to a safe place the National Museum of Archaeology of
Guatemala, its shape and location leave the team with no doubt that it is an altar
For sacred rituals we have evidence on the surface of this altar of something being burned sometime
type of ritual that involved fire the types of rituals that have been performed here are difficult
to imagine the rituals that in other places involve fire also involved some form
Blood sacrifice, torture and death were central to the Mayan belief in the
Sacred altars were used for ceremonies to appease the gods with human sacrifices.
Guatemalan archaeologist Alejandro González began excavating the altar more than a year ago.
year I'm a little nervous anxious and a little happy at the same time it's the most monument
big one that we are going to extract and move from the site and the final result makes us a little nervous
Right now we are preparing the scaffolding that will be necessary to raise the altar.
Made of solid limestone, it weighs twice as much as a grand piano. This is
the moment we've been waiting for a year So we'll see how it goes
[Music] everything works
[Music]
the time has come
hour ago we saw how the altar moved a little and I was thinking that this is
The first time this altar has been moved in the last 15 years
All this is getting very tense both my nerves and the
rope for archaeologists the inscriptions on the altar are the most important, they contain clues to the
epic rise of the Mayan Serpent Kings hidden in their delicate and intricate
The altar carvings represent a powerful king with a crown and his name is Ch Tok.
Ich a known Ally of the Kings snake an inscription
longer even tells us when it was dedicated May 12, 544 after
Christ until this discovery no one knew that
The mighty Chu To Ich had nothing to do with the crown at all.
but the inscriptions on the altar to the serpent king fit with the
New discoveries revealed on the laar map from the crown This is exactly the
direction one should take to go to Calacumul, the capital of Los Reyes
snake turns out that the causeway and the newly revealed settlements of Marchelo
They are on their way to the capital city of the snake far to the north
What we think is happening is that for the kings
snake could operate in the rest of the Mayan World they needed to go through the
corona lipos all this good Let's remove all that stuff back in the old
Plaza de la corona Marchelo and his team have been working in the scorching heat for 8 hours
gradually raising the altar from the ground
lifted we are holding his weight and now we are just trying to
guide it ends the
Time is our last chance because we are going to lose daylight
In half an hour, in less than an hour, it will get dark after more than years on the ground
in the airef ef [Music]
Efim there is no turning back a ton of ancient altara hangs from a fragile
scaffolding in the jungle [Applause] the night is coming fast and the altar is not yet up
[Music]
sure my God is in the truck is in the truck is already up very
Well I don't want to find another monument in my life
[Applause]
in the end it
They did 12 and a half hours of work but the altar finally goes to the city
From Guatemala I am ecstatic I am exhausted but ecstatic
[Music]
Back at the Guatemala-Mexico border, the rain finally cleared.
And I am with the archaeologist Omar Alcover in search of another city
[Music] old we just traveled 15 km along the river in this thick jungle and
deep and now we are in one of the most important archaeological sites
In the entire Mayan World, however, we are still in the most remote part of the jungle.
Guatemalan I have already explored a powerful fortress in
macabil ero now I'm heading to an ancient city called Piedras
Blacks far beyond the area of the study of pacun Omar is part of a team that
uses a new technology that could be revolutionary for the
archaeology here have been applying the liaison using
Drones are more flexible than using conventional aircraft and much more
Affordable for now, this technology is experimental but its potential is enormous
the trees are thick
Here I have built the first data map of Piedras Negras on my reality platform
enlarged and I hope it will allow me to see through this dense jungle of treeless trees.
surprising is a building
Wow, look at that, what could it be? Yes, it's a pyramid. This is incredible, it's like a window to the
past is incredible I mean this is It's almost like magic suddenly
You can erase the trees and there you have it for the first time thanks to the drone I can see
the ancient remains of what were once the giant pyramids of a luxurious royal court
Excavations are even helping to predict what the
[Music] buildings are so different from the first fortress of macabil ero Omar does not doubt
that this royal court was built by a different group of Mayan people and believes that the two groups
They were at war, something happened between macabil ero and here I am referring to
that macabil ero was abandoned but piedras negra rose not only in power but in
population and size immediately after they left Macabil ero had to have happened
It is intriguing to think that 2000 years ago this luxurious royal court of Piedras
Negras may have been at war with the nearby settlement of Macabil Omar
believes the conflict may have continued for over 600 years until around 350
after Christ when the fortress of Macabil fell and its settlement was
abandoned Piedras Negras was victorious and flourished into a powerful kingdom
Maya its name in ancient Mayan could be yib What does that mean something like home of
the turtle lords turtle lords This is how the royal court identified themselves as the
Lords of the Turtles, we are standing on the sacred grounds
of the ancient lords of the turtle right now with a window that world
In Mayan mythology turtles were important, their shells were associated
with gods of the earth and represented the cracked ground where the plants grew
crops the lords of the turtles of Piedras Negras were the lords of the land that gave
life Look at this This is a real room it is the entrance to one of
They exploring the great royal court of Piedras Negras I can still feel their
power Look at these huge stairs And these mounds in Terraces basically we are
watching the blood, sweat and tears of hundreds and hundreds of people along the way
of generations Yes that is what highlights the power that these Kings had capable of
mobilize all the resources and people that were necessary to build a
Space like this really accentuates the power of the Turtle Lords. Here
And now, after centuries of decline, modern archaeology and the avant-garde
Drone footage may fully reveal this incredible ancient palace for the first time
time before deidar most of what we knew about the Mayan war came from
drawings that depicted ritual conflict and the capture of Kings but now that is changing
completely revealed by new technology that's what laar was showing us we are right in
the summit a fortified citadel in the heart of the Mayan World with walls and watchtowers
and even rare and incredible evidence of a war altar is a great find an altar
ritual that connects the city of the crown with the powerful warrior dynasty of the serpent kings
This is the first time this altar has been moved in the last 15 years and a settlement pointing
towards its capital far to the north There it is, it is the main structure, it is not grand
All the newly discovered evidence about this conflict thanks to technology is
a much more sophisticated idea of conflict and war than you think when you see images of
The Mayan kings capturing a single person by the hair in battle that's just a
event this tells us that it is not something on a small scale This is a panorama that was plagued
of conflicts for centuries that is something we would never have been able to say without the messing with
Tens of thousands of new discoveries still waiting to be explored is incredible.
A revolution in our field is changing the way we do archaeology.
The Mayans, the jungles of Central America have many more secrets to share.
Definitely speaking of a period before the Laar and after the Laar in Mayan archaeology
and everything we know now will be different from what we knew before
It's a big change it feels like the invention of tomography or x-ray but for the
Archaeology from high in the sky to beneath the trees in the depths of the World
Maya archaeologists are still beginning to reveal the extraordinary world of one of the
greatest ancient civilizations of our planet the mysterious jungle kingdoms of the
[Music]
Mayans and [Music]